Tekstet av Nicolai Winther
The American Wild Lost advancedürlichs
pong
This exhibition was planned to commemorate
the end of the war. The works of the
painters who played an active part in the
United States, Kuniyoshi Yasuo, Henry
Sugimoto, and Usui Bunpei, are exhibited.
中でも一際目を引くのが、
共生収容所の中で描かれた日系人画家たちの作品です。
彼らは収容所の中で屈辱に耐えながら、
絵画によって希望を見出そうと絵筆を取りました。
KONNICHIWA
でも50年間くらいから50年間くらいにあんなにたくさんの方が向こうに渡って絵を描いていたという事実は僕もある意味では初めてで非常にびっくりしたんですよね。
尾端千代という名前はご存知でした?
全然知らなかったんですよ。やっぱり非常に印象的で素晴らしい絵を描いていらっしゃるので、なんで今まで知らなかったんだろうと思って非常に自分の不勉強を恥じたという。
I also first met Obata Chura, but he had
been drawing pictures to protect his
culture and humanity in the camp. Obata
Chura was the leader. Obata Chura had a
great influence on the American art
movement on the West Coast. I went to the
West Coast to investigate. I went to the U
.S. to interview them.
San Francisco, the west coast of the U.S.
This town, which had many Japanese
immigrants since ancient times, became the
stage of the activities of Chihura Obata
and his friends.
The non-fiction writer Tetsuro Shimojima
Shimojima-san has been interviewing
Japanese painters of the Shuyo-jo for more
than 10 years. Shimojima-san says that he
discovered something unexpected in the
life of the Shuyo-jo while visiting the
Shuyo-jo many times and listening to the
people involved.
下の話を聞くうちに収容所の生活に意外な側面があったことを発見したと下島さんは言います。
4年間という長い収容所生活が絵のために非常に充実し、
そしてむしろ楽しんだというようなことをおっしゃる人が多数いらっしゃるんですね。
収容所時代が充実していたと。 そうですね。 I was surprised and
surprised to find that I met a painter
called Chihura Obata about three years
ago.
日本画家小畑千浦は1903年、明治36年にアメリカに渡りました。 Sumiei-ya
Suisai-ga-de Nishi-kaigan-no-Bijitsukai-no
-Chumoku-o-Atsume, Nochi-ni California-Dai
-gaku Barclay-ko-no-Kyo-ju-ni-Batteki-sa
-remashita.
Obata Chiura-ga-nakunaru-made-sunde-ita
Barclay-no-ie-wo-tazure-mashita.
Hello! Konnichiwa!
Nice to see you again! Og O'Bata-san, Ojo
-san, Yuri-san. Yuri-san. Joroshiku
onegaishimasu. Sakurai desu, Najimichi.
Joroshiku onegaishimasu, Sakurai desu,
Najimichi. Joroshiku onegaishimasu,
Sakurai desu, Najimichi. Please come in.
Ega demo arimasu ka? Hai. Aremo so desu
ka? So, papa ga kakimashita. Magnolia to
Blue Jay. Magnolia. Mokuren no hana. So,
so. Nante, Tori totemo suki datta kaku no.
Shiji kakimashita. Atelier wa arimasen
deshita. Itsumo kazoku ni kakomarete,
dining room de e wo kaiti ita toigetodesu.
Koko ga ja atelier gawari de. Dokoni
suwatta kaiti deshita? Kocchi suwatte,
window ga minna akete. E, tottemu suki
datta koko de yaru no. He.
Donna fuu ni shite kaite rashitan deshou
ne? Omoite rashimasu ka? Sou, papa wa
baseball tottemu suki datta. Yakyuu ga.
Sou, dakara radio koko mimi ni irete, kou
yate kaite. Kikinagara? Sou, toki-toki
Giants ga makeuta, aaa te okotte. I
thought I was a little too much. I thought
you were going to write a poem, but it
didn't work. That's what happened.
Chura Obata was born in 1885, in the year
of 18, in Okayama.
His real name is Zoro Sato.
千代に住む兄六一の養子になりました。
千代七歳の時の絵です。
元々絵の得意だった千代は、日本画家だった六一の影響を受け、自らも画家になることを決意します。
Chura, who was taught by Rokuichi, was
only 17 years old when he won the Japanese
Art Museum's Grand Prize, and won the
first prize. However, the following year,
he suddenly went to the United States.
The world is wide, and there are tens of
millions of people.
人たちがいます。
地浦の書であると言わせる策を成して帰ります。
アメリカに渡った地浦はスクールボーイをしたり、
日経新聞のイラストを描いて生活を始めます。
渡米して9年目、27歳の時に描いた千浦書記の代表作です。
大地に立つおゆうしい少女は、結婚して間もない新妻、春子です。
薄草とした杉木立ち。
太い幹や枝の一本一本が炭の濃淡によって巧みにかき分けられています。
足元には大地から生命を受けた小さな草が群生し、花を結んでいます。
Haruko's expectations and concerns, which
had already taken a new life,
are symbolically depicted in the
transparent air at dawn. 象徴的に描かれています。
母なる大地を描くことによって、
アメリカでの日本画の新境地を開いた千浦は、 創作意欲をかきたてられ、
次々と新しいテーマを求めて旅を重ねます。
膨大な作品が地下の倉庫に残っていました。
Yosemite Valley Where did you draw that
painting? Yes, this is a painting that was
done in Yosemite Valley in 1938, right
before the war. You were drawing Yosemite?
Right. Grandpa used to go to the valley
every summer for camping. Oh, every
summer. And sketching and painting and of
course fishing. Of course fishing. That
was before the war.
A storm that strikes the national park of
Yosemite.
It is a dynamic depiction of the dramatic
changes of nature.
1927年尾端千浦はカリフォルニア大学バークレー校の美術教授ワースライダーとともに寄せ見てを訪れました。そして2ヶ月にわたってキャンプ生活をしながら寄せ見ての大自然を描きました。
At that time, Yosemite was a
representative monument in the United
States, and was painted by many painters.
However, Yosemite, painted by Japanese
painter Obata Chiura, made the Americans
feel the appearance of Yosemite that had
never been seen before.
Chihura's Yosemite series has further
enhanced his reputation.
Monterey, very beautiful area. And grandpa
enjoyed painting the ocean and the scenery
there. Monterey's coast. Monterey to the
south. Matsu is in the middle, and it's
very Japanese. Yes. Chiura has grown up in
Sendai since he was five years old. I
think there's a scene of Matsushima Bay in
the corner of his head. I think the
scenery remains, but the name Shura was
also taken from Matsushima Bay.
So you were looking for such a scenery. I
always had it in my head, and I think I
wandered through California in the United
States. I think I was lost.
The famous school in the United States,
the University of California, Berkeley.
Obata Chura, who returned from Yosemite,
was invited as a Japanese artist of this
university.
雨をかきたいならば雨に打たれよ。
風をかきたいならば風に吹かれよ。
そして何千もの心のレンズを通して書きなさい。
中羅の講義は学生たちの絶大なる支持を受けました。
OVATA CHIURA K幾 moga engelska tannt
atrevet으니까 Laughteriere atlyaltisvina
Fogwa? Sure, Aristok sperm'angi In
California
fyska
etn 보시 gila Denne farben heter Tjurablu.
Kino-ji har skrevet med iwainogu.
Tjurablu har skrevet med iwainogu.
Teksting av Nicolai
Winther
千と色彩で躍動的な女性たちを描き出しています。
1930年代アメリカでは新しい美術の動きが出ていましたこの作品にも当時のアメリカ中小表現主義の影響が伺えます
Obata Chiura I'm sorry.
1941年太平洋戦争が始まる直前に書かれた地滑り
日系人たちの不安が表現されています。
1942年2月ルーズベルト大統領令によって西海岸の日系人およそ12万人が適正外国人として強制収容されることになりました尾端中良も家族とともにサンフランシスコの南のタンホランにある仮収容所に入れられます
Do you remember the day you got together
at the meeting place of the Tampere? Yes,
I remember. It was raining that day, and I
was very sad. I took a bus to the Bay
Bridge and came to Tampere. I put my horse
in the stable. The old horse? I was
thirteen at that time, so I loved horses
very much. I was happy to be able to enter
the stable.
Were you happy? Yes. Mama was so
disappointed. There was an army bed, a
mattress with straws. Mama sat there and
cried. Mama was a person who never cried.
She was very strong. I was surprised and
asked her why she was crying. I heard it.
I was so sad to hear that I was living
with my mother.
I never thought about it.
I often said that the sea was mud. I said
it was ridiculous. I was taken by the mud,
and I finally rolled into the horse shed.
日本語遠く離れ、異郷の地で永遠と築いてきたものすべてを失ってしまった日系人たち。
絶望の淵に追いやられた姿を見て、尾端千浦は美術学校の開設を思い立ちます。
開校は収容されてから25日目のことです。
長年住み慣れし都を離れ、浮草の境遇と似たる生活に入ったのでありますが、
若き人、幼き人の先行きを思うとき明日に希望を捨てることはできません来る日の準備をすべく今、一日一日を新たなる希望を持っていかなくてはいけません以上の趣旨でここにタンフォーラン美術学校を設立いたします
日系人の誇りをもって生きよう。 勇気をもとう。
尾端中良の呼びかけは大きな共感を呼び、
やがて生徒は数百人にも上りました。
Meketre, 6-year-old, ojisan, obasan, minna
ki mastya kakko ni. Yorokonde minna ki
mastya. Haite sugu warito dekita nesu.
Sou, tomodachi, Berkeley no professor and
students ni tanonde kami to enogu to fude
naka minna okutte chodai te tanomi mastya.
みんな友達集めて持ってきましたよ。
それで始めました。
全米に本格的な収容所が完成すると、
日系人たちは各地へ移送されていきます。
1942年9月、尾端千浦は家族とともに
豊洲の砂漠地帯のトパーズ収容所へ送られました。
千浦はここにも美術学校を作ったのです。
私の目の前のこの有志鉄線
この有志鉄線が収容所の鉄線です
50年前の鉄線が今も残っていました
この鉄線のこちら側が収容所の敷地で 広大なこの砂漠の中に
バラックが立ち並んでいたんです 本当に何にもないんですが
遥か彼方向にトパーズさん
今度はトパーズ収容所の名前の由来となったトパーズさんが見えるだけなんですね。
今私が立っているこの辺りに美術学校があったということなんです。
砂漠地帯の真ん中に建てられた収容所には、バラック以外何もなく、
日系人たちは生活に必要なものすべてを自分たちの手で作らなければなりませんでした。
昼は灼熱の太陽が照りつけ、夜は凍てつく寒さが襲います。
一度砂嵐が吹き始めると、一週間もの間吹き荒れました。
バラックの中では隙間から侵入する細かい砂との戦いが一日中続きました。
Teksting av Nicolai
Winther
屋根もなく、電燈もなく、ストーブもなく、
土凍る高原の夜の寒さ肌を刺す。
屋具も足らず、みぞれふる鉄椒。
七人連れの囚われの旅に心身共に疲れ果てたるサンタアナ寄りの人々
I was very disappointed. I entered a very
big place. There was nothing. There was no
tree. I cried hard. Gammatte naita. Daka
papa, dooshite mo yama no hon ni minasai.
Me wa ati no hon ni minasai. Kirei na
sunset, sunrise ga ala. Dooshite mo nature
ga yoku surute. Shizenga. Gammatte.
Spirit, jibun no kimochi ga yoku narte.
Susume mashita.
Obata Chiura was convinced that looking at
the beauty of nature leads to hope for
tomorrow.
The water tower, the symbol of the camp,
and the clouds dyed in the sunset. 雲や雲。
過酷な条件の中で、千浦の美術学校に込めた思いが感じられる作品です。
Topaz Art School opened several art
exhibitions before the end of the war.
From Tampo Land to Topaz, there were
friends who supported the art school
started by Obata Chura.
日系二世のミネ・オークボー。
カリフォルニア大学バークレー校の美術学生だった彼女は、
タンホラン美術学校ではチューラと共に教師として参加しました。
Mine Okubo Mine Okubo is a work of art
that depicts the world of despair and
suffering using wood.
Hibi Hisako draws the life of a
housekeeper in detail from her mother's
point of view. 中心から収容所の中の生活を細やかに描いています。
トッパーズ農場の収穫物
作品の裏には砂漠の荒野で果物と野菜を育て、届けてくれたトパーズの日本人農民に捧げると書かれています。
日比久子の夫、日比松桜の作品には小用手が度々登場します。
Candy
自由の象徴でもあります。
日比松三郎は尾端千浦にとって
渡米して間もない頃からの親友でした。
丹波蘭からトパーズへと美術学校を運営していく上で 欠かせない協力者でした。
丹波蘭の美術学校を創立する時も Chiyura consults with them
daily. With their cooperation, the art
school is built.
They are worried about whether the
students will come. They are worried about
whether the students will come. On the
opening day, it was a big storm and it was
raining cold. On the opening day, it was a
big storm and it was raining cold.
妻 SHEING P الس般 I think it was a very
passionate feeling.
The men who draw pictures in the twilight
of Topaz. The joy of being able to draw in
the Yushitesu line appears in the back.
トパーズ美術学校で日比松三郎に絵の手ほどきを受けた人が今も健在でした。
ダン・ハラダさん72歳。日系2世として19歳の時に収容されました。
Harada-san was instructed to put a canvas
on Hibi Matsusaburo, and he began to draw.
The test for the neutralization of America
in 1943 changed his fate. Harada's life
changed. The question was, can you deny
the loyalty to the emperor? If you receive
an order, do you have the will to fight as
an American soldier? Harada answered these
questions with no. Because of that, Harada
was sent to the camp of Tool Lake, where
only Japanese people with anti-American
feelings were gathered.
Barak, a painting
by Mr. Harada, is a black shadow
that wraps around the barrack. It
represents Mr. Harada's feelings at the
time.
Harada-san is walking in the camp at
night, and he says that it looked as if
the barracks were lonely and looked like
themselves. 自分たちのようだったと語っています。
秦さんにとって収容所時代というのは人生の中でどんな意味を持つのでしょうか?
非常に今でも非常に Nante imasu ka, kokoro
no naka ni, hitosu no kizu demo arimasu
kedo, sore to douji ni, watashi ni totte
wa ijou ni kreative na, eio kakuge de
kreative na, jujitsu
shita shidai deshita.
The four years of the school were days of
humiliation for the Nikkei people.
But the art school was a source of life,
no doubt.
August 14, 1945, Japan time, August 15,
Hibi Matsusaburo left a painting on the
day of the final battle.
There is a man who is wandering around
Kobe in the west of his homeland.
廃墟
尾端千浦が広島に落とされた原爆のニュースを聞いて描いた作品です。
尾端千浦はこの絵を最後に、戦争にまつわる絵は二度と描きませんでした。 zombie
врем
戦後なんですが、尾端千代は大学に復職しまして、
バークレー校の名誉教授を務めた後、退職するんですね。
その後は文化の架け橋としてアメリカに日本の文化を紹介するということに人生を捧げたんですね。
文化の架け橋ということでいうと、たくさんの画家たちがアメリカに渡って、
国と国との間の文化を結ぼうとするわけですけど、 国と国との戦争という運命によって
強制収容所内が入れられてしまうと
そこで大端千浦と日比松浦という人がやった
非常に大きな動きですよね 美術学校を作るという
それは非常に力強いものになっていたという意味では 貴重だったときがするんですよ
生活的に言うと 段原田さんが書いたりとか 美濃大久保さんが書いたりとか
ああいうくらいのところだったと思うんですけど それを何とかして変えていこうという
その意思みたいなものは 非常に貴重だなって気がしますね。
それにしても、トパーズのね、 京成終業時の後に行ったんですけど、 本当に猛烈な風で、
あの日ちょうど気温が38度でしてね、 もうちょっとこういるだけで、
日差しが本当に強くて、ジリジリ痛いくらいなんですよね。
で、あれだけの過酷な厳しい条件の中でも、 絶望しないで絵を描き続けたと、
非常に強靭な精神力ですかね、 それを思うんですが、 でも一方で、絵を見ますと、
非常にその透明感がある、伸びやかな絵も非常に多いんですよね。
透明感というものがですね、本当に京成修行の中でもね、
ある種の高い志と言いましょうか、
志を表すものなのかな、そういう思いをして描いてきたんですけれどもね。
尾形千代の絵の特質というのは、やはりその大胆で軽やかなところだと思うんですよね。
それがあってこそ、やっぱりその母なる大地のようなところで、
緻密なそういう日本画の技法があるんですが、
でも、それを遥かに超えて、心情までも表すような、
抽象表現主義のような形というものがあって、
その軽やかさが、やっぱりそういう意味でいうと、
希望をもたらすというか、そういう感じがあったんだろうなという気がしますね。
その象徴的な色がチューラブルーですか、真っ青な、
本当カリフォルニアの青と、チューラブルー。本当に印象的でしたけれどもね。
オワタチューラの作品は日本で初公開ですが、その中羅の作品多数を含めますアメリカに生きた日系人画家たちの展覧会、10月1日までですが、東京都の庭園美術館で開かれています。
その後、大分と広島でも開かれる予定になっています。
Undertexter av Nicolai Winther
Undertexter av Nicolai
Winther
Undertexter av
Undertexter av Nicolai Winther
M driver hits the floor.
Ohh!
многedd velder Please take a closer look.
When you touch the switch...
The heart... It becomes like this. That's
the title of the game.
This time, it's a self-destruction. It's
interesting. It's interesting. I think the
robot is waiting for someone. It's saying
it's irritated. It's stepping on the
ground. It looks like it's stepping on a
tap. It feels very humorous.
作品は機械を取り入れることによって動きを生み出している作品です。
生物を思わせる人質的な動きは、SLDを除く蒸気機関によるものです。
Nanamimata doishu no takuhin wa说
上記やお盛りといった saikino dewa oda miruko de ni
kihome
ta Duos, haritнакомe sko. Idet 써,
forinatisig帔ithiais Always-to-Be.
разбaktt pål gettin som er b theCUBE sound
Unver antioxidant, kayию Проío …
A eleven barrel brinecychлён du
spontaneous jum Nerdонд주고 som kan regna
van vra 만큼 utukes jega stille. Det셨, eit
gemaakt anld atmosfé 64 eit fogsj
inflation erindert … S classified in New
Zealand
Studies ,
Undertexter av
Undertekster av Ai-Media
Undertexter av Nicolai
Winther